Hello, everyone.
Hello.
Good morning.
Thank you.
My name is Minkyung Kim from Korea.
You can call me MK.
It's a pleasure to meet you.
Are you ready to listen to English?
This is my third time being in Taiwan and
every experience has been amazing.
Thank you again for inviting me.
And before we dive into session, I would
like to tell you about my background
to help you better understand what you can
take away from today's session.
I studied education and after that I
worked as a teacher for seven years.
And during that time I got interested in
coding so I decided to seriously explore
coding.
So I joined Apple Developer Academy as a
learner.
There with my team we made a macOS app
called iWaver that automatically places
large volume of PDF pages.
The following year I joined the academy as
its first learning development mentor.
And I acquired another degree in computer
science after that.
And I'm also doing my masters in Edtech
right now. So I'm doing research in fields
like learning data analytics or content
design strategies and gamification.
This year I'm expanding my role as a
learning lead overseeing learning
experience in academy.
And also I'm supporting mentors'
educational skills.
So as you might have guessed from my
journey, I'm an education specialist,
not a technical expert, so I'm going to
share what you can take away and apply to
your apps.
And you are the technical experts and you
are the ones who can bring these
strategies
and make it real in life.
So what am I here to talk about?
Let's go back to the title.
Designing Adaptive UX through Learning Theory and
AI.
So what does UX have to do with learning?
When you think about the moment
you first download an app,
you need to figure out how it works.
Where are the buttons?
What should I do?
How can I accomplish my goal?
So that is, at its core, a learning
experience.
So today I'm going to view user experience
as a form of learning experience.
And if we do that, we can get some help,
we can get some hints from educators.
Because they have spent a lot of time
trying to figure out
how to effectively support learners.
Let's look at some questions they have
been trying to answer for decades.
How do we help learners persist instead of
giving up?
How do we provide the right level of
support so learners can learn
independently?
And how do we keep learners continuously
engaged?
But today we are going to use the
perspective of viewing user experience as
a learning experience.
So let's try
to change the word
"learn" into "use"
So how do we help?
Can anyone guess?
Users, thank you.
Users.
users persist instead of
giving up?
And how do we provide the right level of
support so...
Great, thank you.
Users can?
Use! Amazing. Use independently.
And the last one, how do we keep
Perfect.
How do we keep users
continuously engaged?
And I hope you can now see what I'm trying
to tell you.
So I'm going to introduce three learning
theories.
The basic ones, I'm not going to explain
too much.
I'll bring lots of examples and the
strategies as well.
So I'm going to talk about the cognitive
load theory and then ZPD,
Zone of Proximal Development and
Scaffolding.
And the last one is the flow theory.
So the first one, the cognitive load
theory.
This was introduced by Dr. John Sweller
in 1988.
And we all know about working memory.
We all know that we should not exceed
working memory.
So the core idea of cognitive load theory
is that when designing for learning,
we should avoid exceeding the limits of
working memory so that learners can stay
focused on the task itself.
This theory introduces three types of
load.
Intrinsic load, extraneous load, and
germane load.
The first is intrinsic load, which refers to
the inherent complexity of the task
itself.
The second is extraneous load, which comes
from unnecessary or inefficient elements
that are not directly related to the task.
So it distracts the learner.
The last one, the germane load, it is the
effort required to build schemas.
It's the mental structure that supports
learning, so it links the new information
to the current information.
And we should minimize one thing, maximize
another, and manage the rest.
So can you guess which one we should
minimize?
All of them?
If some things are inherent, we cannot
really deal with it, do anything with it.
But we should minimize extraneous load.
These are unnecessary mental effort caused
by poor instructional design
or distracting presentation.
So we should minimize it by removing irrevalant information,
using clear and concise information
and avoiding uncluttered layout or unnecessary animations.
Now I feel safe.
Can you guess which one we should
maximize?
Yes.
Some of you were pointing, and that's
correct.
We should maximize the germane load.
That is where learning happens.
So this is a productive mental effort used
to actually process the information,
build schemas, and commit to long-term memory.
So we should maximize it by encouraging
deep thinking or self-reflection and
helping learners connect new concepts to
their prior knowledge.
And the last one, we should manage
intrinsic load.
We should manage it because intrinsic load
is inherent difficulty of the task itself,
so there is not much we can do.
But we can help them or we can guide them
through
making them in smaller digestible
chunks and also sequencing it logically
from simple to complex.
Now back to our app and the user.
If we throw too much at a user, they
experience an extraneous load, they get
overwhelmed, and they might leave.
So we need to minimize this so they can
focus on the core value.
Now let's take a look at some examples
of how these strategies for reducing
cognitive load can be applied into UX.
Does anyone use Chrome here?
Yay, thank you. I do too.
And when you press Command plus P, whether
in Chrome or not, usually, can you guess
what happens?
P? Print!
Yeah, you're right. Thank you.
Print!
So print dialog pops up.
But when this dialog pops up, it does not
show you 100 settings.
It only asks its destination and pages,
like the range of pages, and the layout,
landscape or portrait.
So it only asks three questions.
But if you're a power user and if you want
more, of course you can simply click more
settings and then you can adjust a lot of
things.
So at first, a system presents a
simplified view.
If all of these detailed options were
presented to the user at the moment they
tried to do it the first time, it would
create a massive cognitive bottleneck.
So instead, the system completely removes
that initial mental barrier.
And Apple highlighted this exact concept
back in WWDC 2022.
So if you're interested, you can check out
"The Craft of SwiftUI APIs: Progressive
Disclosure."
Now let's take a look at Airbnb.
So when I open the app and when I start
searching, it does not overwhelm me with
information.
It only asks where.
And then just when.
And next, who.
So by chunking the information, Airbnb
reduces cognitive load at the beginning,
allowing users to focus on the core task,
which is browsing and choosing a place to
stay.
But actually, if the user next time opens
the app
they are given a shortcut so they can focus on what matters most, which is browsing and choosing.
It already has a shortcut of Taipei,
everything, and it automatically shows the
result right away.
And another example is autofill.
So this is something that we can go even
further and eliminate the behavioral load
entirely.
When you receive a text message with
authentication code, we used to have to go
to the message and maybe memorize the
numbers and type in.
But now, it automatically detects the code
and it will surface the numbers above the
keyboard, so you can just tap it and it
gets filled right away.
So this is like zero cognitive friction.
And let me introduce the CapWords.
This is a 2025 Apple design award winner
for delight and fun.
And with Apple's frameworks, it replaces
manual data input with more seamless
interactions.
Let me show you.
It has a sound, but unfortunately, we
can't hear it.
I'll just move on.
So let me summarize what you can apply.
I'm going to give you what you can apply
to your apps.
So first, you should limit distractions.
And then use clear language.
Group related information.
Avoid unnecessary details.
And emphasize important content.
And beyond these, any approach that helps
reduce cognitive load is relevant.
And I'm just giving you only five, but any
approach will do.
Now the second theory, ZPD and
Scaffolding.
The Zone of Proximal Development.
It was introduced by Lev Vygotsky, and the
Scaffolding was developed by Jerome
Bruner.
And these two concepts provide a clear
framework for when and how to intervene
when a learner is learning a new thing.
There are three zones.
Zone A is something a learner can do alone
without any help, so a learner has already
mastered it.
Zone C is something a learner cannot do
even with the help.
This is beyond their level, so they cannot
do even with the guidance.
And Zone B is where a learner can do with
proper help.
So this is where the learning happens, and
this is called the Zone of Proximal
Development.
And this is the sweet spot that we need to
focus and provide proper guidance and
help.
Can anyone guess what these structures are
outside of the building?
It's called scaffolding, yes.
These are scaffolding.
So you use scaffoldings when you're
constructing so that workers can go higher and
build a building.
And after a building can stand on its own,
after it's stable, then you take these
scaffoldings away.
So like this, we should provide proper
help and guidance, but as the learner
progresses, we should take them away.
So at first we provide full support, and
then we slightly decrease the assistance.
And then the final goal will be for the
users to do things independently.
Let's take a look at some examples.
Swift Playground.
This helps through a series of dynamic
scaffolds.
The app provides glossary popovers and
code completion bars that suggest the
exact syntax needed at first.
But as the user progresses to later
chapters, the hints become less
prescriptive and more conceptual.
So eventually the guided completion bar is
replaced by a standard keyboard, removing
the entire scaffolding.
Tips from Apple is also a great example of
scaffolding and also reducing cognitive
load.
Instead of overwhelming the user with a
full manual or complex documentation, it
delivers small, digestible tips over time.
So it introduces features gradually, often
through short, focused pieces of guidance
or occasional notification.
And as users become familiar, that support
fades away. And if the user uses
shortcuts, then they do not give you any
more tips.
So it appears when you are near the skill
but haven't mastered it yet. And when the
user has mastered it, then it stops.
The scaffolding doesn't have to be a text
tooltip.
So if you look at the Goodnotes, when a
user draws a crooked shape, then algorithm
detects it and makes it into a perfect
shape.
It acts as an invisible scaffold for
drawing beginners, and it makes them feel
capable.
Notion is actually a very interesting
example because it's a powerful and quite
complex tool, yet it works hard to reduce
that complexity for new users.
So when you first start, Notion doesn't
overwhelm you with all the features.
It simply tells you
"Press space for AI or slash for commands".
And when you press slash,
Notion reveals a wide range of
features, and by just hovering on them, it
gives you the short descriptions or
examples.
So Notion steps in lightweight guidance,
and over time, users remember the commands
and no longer need the prompts.
To apply ZPD and scaffolding to UX, here
are a few principles to follow.
And please remember, in practice, we don't
apply just one learning theory, and these
approaches work best when it's all
combined together.
So it should detect users' hesitation.
Give contextual hints.
Offer temporary support.
Fade assistance gradually. And
then empower independent action.
The last one is a flow theory coined by
Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi.
And I'm pretty
sure you all have heard of him.
So the flow theory is, if you want your
user to be fully immersed, you have to
meticulously calibrate the difficulty of
their experience.
So if your app is too challenging, then
users feel anxiety, and they feel worried,
frustrated, and they might leave. They might quit.
But if it's too easy, they get bored, and
they quit.
So you have to keep them right between
them so that users can still stay in the
flow state.
This is all. Let's take a look at some
examples of how the strategies of flow can
be applied.
Elevate is a brain training app.
It is a strong example of how learning experiences
can be designed around flow theory.
So as you play the games, the on-device
algorithm constantly analyzes the accuracy
and reaction speed in the background.
So it dynamically calibrates the math or
language difficulty so that learners can
stay in the flow state.
This can be understood through
ZPD, where app identifies the gap between
the user's current ability to potential
through data.
So from a scaffolding perspective,
the app learns user behavior and provides timely
hints for support when needed.
And ultimately, the app behaves like a
teacher, so even allowing for gradual
removal of support over time.
I'm pretty sure you all know Duolingo.
This is actually a great example of
educational app that goes beyond flow
theory.
Duolingo applies so many strategies, and
it delivers personalized learning from the
data.
And also, it suggests a new goal,
and it uses a lot of gamification strategies like
rankings and badges and nudges and
everything
to just keep learners stay
focused and engaged.
I'm a heavy user with a streak over
2,100 days.
And whenever I see this "JUMP HERE?"
button, I feel like I'm being challenged,
and I'm like, "Okay, challenge accepted."
And I end up learning more than I planned.
Apple Fitness does this amazingly as well.
So each week, it recommends a new move
goal
that's tailored to its user. So it
does not give you the exact same
10,000-step goal to everyone.
The system analyzes the past activity to
set a personalized monthly challenge or
weekly challenge so that it pushes you
slightly higher yet achievable.
To apply flow theory to UX, here are a few
principles to follow.
Track user progress.
Adjust task difficulty. Set achievable
goal.
Balance skill and challenge. And
prevent boredom and frustration.
Well, all of these three theories work
great if it's combined together.
So I encourage you to think and maybe apply
them to your app.
And based on everything we've discussed,
the cognitive flow theory,
ZPD and
scaffolding, and the flow theory,
I would also like to recommend this video, which
brings these ideas together into a
practical UX design guidance.
And also, this year,
they also have this
new video.
It's only about 17 minutes
long, and it covers a wide range of
fundamental design principles.
And if you watch it now, then you will maybe
recognize some learning theories in the
back.
Now, let me talk briefly about on-device AI.
Well, I want to be frank with you, and
I know this is not the silver bullet for
every problem. I know its limitations.
But I suggest maybe you can take a look at
on-device AI first, because
of privacy. The user data is really private data.
It's really sensitive, so it's better to stay
on the device.
So if it does not get uploaded on cloud
server, it will be safe.
And the next one is continuity.
If it does
not depend on the internet, and if it
works on the plane or on the elevator,
then learner can stay focused and the
learning doesn't stop. So you can keep
your users hooked and engaged.
The next one is cost. So
cloud servers are
great, but if the data has to always go
back and forth, then it will make you pay
the cost.
So if you can use on-device AI,
it will save you some costs.
Well, while on-device AI offers some
advantages, it does come with some
challenges,
such as battery consumption or
need for high-end hardware.
So, well, you're the technical experts, so it's up
to you to do what I was suggesting.
And if you're interested in exploring
on-device AI further,
I recommend taking a
look at this video from last year. It
offers a great starting point to
understand how to bring these ideas into
practice.
Now let's take a moment to reflect on what
we learned today.
So the first one was the
cognitive load theory. So we should reduce
too much load.
ZPD and scaffolding. The zone of proximal
development. We should target that zone
and provide scaffolding.
And the flow theory. So we need to make
them learn faster and engage deeper and
stay longer. So we can use all these three
theories into our apps.
And by leveraging technology, we can build
interfaces that dynamically adapt to a
user's individual learning curve.
So when we think about adaptive learning
or user experiences,
It's not just about making them smarter.
It's about making them more private, more responsive, and
more sustainable.
Here's my final suggestion.
So when you
notice users dropping off because learning
how to use an app feels confusing or
difficult,
I hope you can get some help by
designing adaptive UX through learning
theory and AI.
That's all I prepared for today, and thank
you all for listening.
This is all.
Thank you!
Thank you.